Guide to the South African Apartheid Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
South African Apartheid Collection
1952-1991
1985-1988
MS 1500
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
31.75
(83 boxes)
The collection documents the apartheid system in South Africa and the different stages of the liberation struggle which was instrumental in bringing about the decline of the system. The collection consists of printed materials such as newsclippings, publications, reports, press releases, newsletters, pamphlets and newspapers of the South African government, parliamentary parties, non-parliamentary groups such as the African National Congress, and American and other foreign groups. Also included in the collection are posters which illustrate the inequities perpetrated by the South African government and the resulting resistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to Manuscripts and Archives by the African Curator, Sterling Memorial Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in nine series and fifteen additions: I. South African Government, 1961-1991. II. South African Parliamentary Parties, 1961-1991. III. Non-Parliamentary/Opposition/ Resistance Groups, 1961-1991. IV. South African Institutes and Foundations, 1966-1991. V. American Government Policy Towards South Africa, 1974-1988. VI. Disinvestment/ Divestment, 1978-1987. VII. American Anti-Apartheid Pressure Groups, 1972-1991. VIII. International Pressure Groups, 1963-1991. IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1970-1990.
Scope and Contents
The South African Apartheid Collection in Sterling Memorial Library. While the collection spans the years from 1961 to 1991, much of the material dates from 1985 to 1988. The collection consists of printed material such as clippings, publications, reports, press releases, newsletters, pamphlets and newspapers. In addition, it includes an interesting and colorful collection of posters which illustrate the atrocities perpetrated by the South African government and he resulting resistance.
The collection is arranged in nine series and fourteen additions, with folders in each series arranged alphabetically and documents within folders arranged chronologically. The series include:
I. South African Government
II. South African Parliamentary Parties
III. Non-Parliamentary/Opposition/Resistance Groups
IV. South African Institutes and Foundations
V. American Government Policy towards South Africa
VI. Disinvestment/Divestment
VII. American Anti-Apartheid Pressure Groups
VIII. International Pressure Groups
IX. Posters and Printed Materials
While the bulk of the material focuses on the opposition to apartheid and the resistance movements, there is very little material which documents government perspectives and arguments. Material on CODESA has not been included in this collection. Also, while the majority of the material on this subject is in this collection, additional material on apartheid is available in the African Collection, Manuscript Group Number 605.
Series I, SOUTH AFRICAN GOVERNMENT, is composed of pamphlets, publications and press releases. A major component of this series is the files released by the Embassy/Consulate, which contained, for the most part, "propaganda" material indicative of government perspectives of the South African problem. Through the newsletters, the embassy promoted government "achievements" by focusing on changes being made in the country, on the improvement of he economy, South Africa's crucial role in the affairs of the region, the "true" face of the African National Congress, the increase in the number of tourists to South Africa and the negotiation process. Also included are brochures published by the Bureau for Information in an attempt to promote the idea of a racially harmonious South Africa as opposed to a violence-plagued country. Materials documenting the emergence of the homeland system, as part of the apartheid master plan to remove Blacks into the rural parts of South africa, have been included in this series.
Series II, SOUTH AFRICAN PARLIAMENTARY PARTIES, contains publications and pamphlets of the country's recognized parliamentary parties. The bulk of the material, which is devoted to the electioneering process in South African politics, provides a lucid explanation of the principles and policies of each of the parties. This series is also helpful in documenting the changing policies of the ruling National Party and the support or opposition it encountered from the other parties in Parliament.
Series III, NON PARLIAMENTARY/OPPOSITION/PRESSURE GROUPS, is the largest single series of the collection. It consists of documents, newsletters, press releases, pamphlets, reports, and publications which chronicle the work of the different organizations within South Africa to fight against or for apartheid. These include white right-wing groups, student organizations, religious organizations, labor organizations, community organizations and previously banned/exiled movements. This series provides an invaluable source which clearly chronicles the struggle against apartheid in South Africa, especially the years 1985-1988, when the anti-apartheid activities gained rapid momentum. The diverse range of organizations involved indicates that the liberation struggle cut across a wide spectrum of South African society. The documents of white right-wing groups who demanded the protection of a white united South Africa provide a sharp contrast with the material of left-wing groups who called for a free and democratic South Africa. In comparison to the other non-parliamentary groups, the history and struggle of the African National Congress is very well documented in this series.
Series IV, SOUTH AFRICAN INSTITUTES AND FOUNDATIONS, includes reports and publications of a host of research institutions and foundations that function in the country. This series provides information on their work and changing views on the South African situation. Many of these institutes, for example the South African Institute of Race Relations, furthered the cause of liberation organizations.
Series V, AMERICAN GOVERNMENT POLICY TOWARDS SOUTH AFRICA, the smallest series of the collection, documents American policy and action towards South Africa, and U. S. strategies of coercing the government to abandon apartheid. It consists of newsletters, pamphlets, official statements, and special reports.
Series VI, DISINVESTMENT/DIVESTMENT, includes newsletters and reports of American organizations and institutions which have not only publicly opposed apartheid, but have also developed schemes to improve the welfare of black South Africans. One of the most effective strategies was to withdraw investments from South Africa. Hence, this series is a source for the divestment/disinvestment issue and its effectiveness as a strategy for change in the country. Many universities, especially Yale and Stanford, were at the forefront of this campaign. Additional material on this strategy can be found in Series IX.
Series VII, AMERICAN ANTI-APARTHEID ORGANIZATIONS, is a fairly large series which focuses on the role of numerous American groups in removing racial oppression in South Africa. Through their newsletters, publications and campaigns, these organizations aimed not only to bring to the attention of the American people the plight of the oppressed, but also to design strategies to build the momentum for legislative action against South Africa. Of particular importance are the files of the Africa Fund, American Committee on Africa, Episcopal Church People for a Free Southern Africa, and the Washington Office on Africa. Through their work these groups were successful in providing medical, financial, and moral assistance to black South Africans and in ultimately influencing American corporate and government policy towards South Africa. Their publications, reports, and newsletters are a good source for information on the violence that was perpetrated in South Africa, especially in Natal.
Series VIII, INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE GROUPS, contains material which focuses on the pressure exerted by non-American groups and their respective government on South Africa to bring an end to apartheid. Although most of these groups are based in Europe, the work of the British anti-apartheid organizations dominates these series.
Series IX, POSTERS AND PRINTED MATERIAL, consists of oversized items, primarily posters and other printed material.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Anti-apartheid movements -- Great Britain; Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Anti-apartheid movements -- United States; Apartheid -- South Africa; Disinvestment; Government, Resistance to -- South Africa; Insurgency -- South Africa; South Africa -- Foreign relations -- United States; Labor unions -- South Africa; Homelands (South Africa); South Africa -- Politics and government -- 1978-1989; United States -- Foreign relations -- South Africa; Buthelezi, Mangosuthu G. (Mangosuthu Gatsha), 1928-; De Klerk, F. W. (Frederik Willem), 1936-; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-2013; Africa Fund (New York, N.Y.); African National Congress; American Committee on Africa; Black Sash (Society); Episcopal Churchpeople for a Free Southern Africa; Inkatha (Organization: South Africa); National Party (South Africa); National Union of South African Students; South African Students' Organisation; United Democratic Front (South Africa); Washington Office on Africa
- South African Government, 1961-1991; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Material in this series focuses on the South African government's methods of maintaining the apartheid system in the country. The files are arranged alphabetically with documents within each folder arranged chronologically.
  - Bureau for Information, 1961-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department of Constitutional Development, 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Department of Education, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department of Foreign Affairs, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of Home Affairs, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Embassy/ Consulate
    - 1964-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Homelands
    - 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1981-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Local government, 1967-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - South African Broadcasting Corporation (SABC), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - South African Police (SAP), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - South African Tourism Board, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- South African Parliamentary Parties, 1961-1991; Series II
  This series contains material on South Africa's recognized parliamentary parties. The files are arranged alphabetically with documents within each folder arranged chronologically.
  - Conservative Party (Consertiewe party), 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Democratic Party (DP), 1974, 1989-1999 (Box 3, Folder 17 - 18)
  - Herstigte Nasionale Party (HNP), 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Independent Party, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Liberal Party, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - National Party (Nasionale Party) (NP)
    General note
    See also: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 33-34
    - 1963-1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 24 - 25)
  - New Republic Party (NRP), 1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Progressive Party, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Progressive Federal Party (PFP)
    - 1973-1987 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Progressive Independent Party, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - South African Independent Party, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - United Party (UP)
    - 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Non-Parliamentary/Opposition/Pressure Groups, 1961-1991; Series III
  Material in Series III chronicles the work of the different organizations within South Africa to fight against or for apartheid. Files are arranged alphabetically while documents within each folder are arranged chronologically. One folder of photographs of children and youth tortured by South African police can be found at the end of the series.
  - Action Group Against Apartheid, undated (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Action Youth, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Ad Hoc Detention Action Committee (ADAC), 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Africa Cooperative Action Trust (ACAT), 1986 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Africa Enterprise, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - African National Congress (ANC)
    See: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 31-32
    - 1973-1984 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - 1989 [report on the ANC-Soviet Social Scientists Seminar] (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - 1989 (Box 7, Folder 44 - 45)
    - 1990 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Posters
  - African People's Democratic Union of South Africa (APDUSA), 1979-1984 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Africanist Patriotic Front, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Afrikaner Volkswag, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Afrikaner Weerstandbeweging (AWB), undated (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Ahmadiyya Movement, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Alexander Youth Congress, undated (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Anti-Censorship Action Group, 1987-1990 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Anti-Labour Bill Campaign, undated (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Anti-Resident's Council Committee, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Anti-Tour Committee, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Athlone Coordinating Committee, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Athlone Education Crisis Committee, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Anthlone Student's Action Committee, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Azanian People's Organisation (AZAPO), 1976-1991 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Azanian Student's Movement (AZASM), 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Azanian Student's Organisation (AZASO), 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Bandwagon (Resistance Publication)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - 1976 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Belville Civic Association, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Black Christmas Committee, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Black Consciousness Movement (BCM), 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Black Sash
    - 1979-1988 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - 1989 (Box 9, Folder 70 - 71)
  - Black Student's Society (BSS), 1988 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Bond van Konsertiewe Afrikaners, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Call of Islam, 1985-1989 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Cape Action League, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Cape Democrats, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Cape Herald Staff Association, undated (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Cape Rebel, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Cape Town Municipal Worker's Association (CTMWA), 1985 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Cape Youth Congress (CAYCO), 1985-1986 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Chemical Workers Industrial Union, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Christian League of Southern Africa, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Civil Rights League, 1962-1985 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Clothing Worker's Union, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Community Arts Project (CAP), 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - Community Resource and Information Centre (CRIC), undated (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Concerned Social Workers and the Organisation for Appropriate Social Services in South Africa (OASSSA), undated (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Congress of South African Students (COSAS), 1982 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU)
    See: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 33-34
    - 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Posters and additional printed material
      See: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 31-32 See: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 33-34
  - Congress of South African Writers, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Consumer Action Committee, undated (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Consumer Support Committee, undated (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Council of Unions of South Africa (CUSA), 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Counter Propaganda Committee, undated (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - David Rabkin Memorial Committee, undated (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Democrats in South Africa, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Detainees Parent's Support Committee, 1982-1987 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Detainees Support Committee (DESCOM), 1983-1987 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Diakonia, 1985-1987 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Ditshwantsho tsa Rona, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Education Action Committee (EAC), undated (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Education Charter Campaign, undated (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Education Resource and Information Centre (ERIC), undated (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Elsie's River Call Group, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - End Conscription Campaign (ECC), 1984-1989 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Fattis and Monis Worker's Support Committee, undated (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Federated Union of Black Arts, undated (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Federation of Cape Civic Association, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Federation of South African Trade Unions (FOSATU), 1984 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Federation of South African Women (FEDSAW), 1989 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Five Freedoms Forum, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Free Azanian, 1984-1988 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Friends and Families of Detainees, undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - From Women, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Gardens Youth Congress, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Garment Worker's Union, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Grahamstown Rural Committee, 1984-1989 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Grahamstown Soccer Association (GRASA), 1983 (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Human Awareness, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Human Rights Commission, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Independent Board of Enquiry into Informal Repression (IBIIR), 1990 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Inkatha
    - 1970-1988 (Box 11, Folder 124)
    - 1990 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - International Labour, Research and Information Group, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Interschool Coordinating Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Isaziso (Transkei)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - 1977 (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - 1978 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Jews for Justice, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Johannesburg Democratic Action Committee (JODAC), 1987-1989 (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Johnny Isset Trial Support Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Joint Civic Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Joint Student Youth Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - June 16th Movement, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Kathovo Youth Congress, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Kraaifontein Civic Association, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Kwa-Zulu Natal Indaba, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Lawyers For Human Rights, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Legal Education and Action Project, undated (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - Let South Africa Speak, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - Lotus River Tenant's Association, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - Macassar Civic Association, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - Manenberg Student's Congress (MASCO), 1985 (Box 12, Folder 146)
  - March Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Masibambane Cooperative Forum, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Media Worker's Association of South Africa (MWASA), 1980 (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - Merit Party, undated (Box 12, Folder 150)
  - Methodist Church, undated (Box 12, Folder 151)
  - Mgwali Resident's Association, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 152)
  - Mitchell's Plain Student's Congress (MIPSCO), undated (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - Musical Editorial Collective, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 154)
  - Muslims Against Oppression, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 155)
  - Muslim Student's Association of South Africa, undated (Box 12, Folder 156)
  - Muslim Youth Movement (MYM), 1988 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - Natal Indian Congress (NIC), 1984 (Box 13, Folder 158)
  - Natal Organisation of Women (NOW), 1987 (Box 13, Folder 159)
  - National Committee Against Removals (NCAR), 1986-1990 (Box 13, Folder 160)
  - National Education Union of South Africa (NEUSA), 1987 (Box 13, Folder 161)
  - National Forum, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 162)
  - National Medical and Dental Association (NAMDA), 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 163)
  - National Student Coordinating Committee, undated (Box 13, Folder 164)
  - National Student Federation, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 165)
  - National Union of Metal Workers of South Africa (NUMSA), 1985 (Box 13, Folder 166)
  - National Union of South African Students (NUSAS)
    - 1961-1983 (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - 1983-1987 (Box 13, Folder 168)
    - 1989 (Box 13, Folder 169)
  - New Unity Movement, 1985-1987 (Box 13, Folder 170)
  - Ninety Day Protest Committee, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 171)
  - Northern Suburbs Interim Teacher's Union, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 172)
  - Oranje Workers, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 173)
  - Pan Africanist Congress (PAC), 1978-1989 (Box 13, Folder 174)
  - Patriotic Press (Voice of the White Workers), 1981-1987 (Box 13, Folder 175)
  - No Folder (Box 13, Folder 176)
  - Pietermaritzburg Agency for Christian Social Awareness and Action, undated (Box 13, Folder 177)
  - Port Alfred Resident's Civic Organisation, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - Program for Social Change, 1974-1976 (Box 14, Folder 179)
  - Projects Committee, undated (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - Ravensmead Youth Student Organisation, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 181)
  - Raymond Suttner Support Group, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 182)
  - Release Mandela Campaign, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 183)
  - Repression Monitoring Group (RMG), 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folder 184)
  - Retail and Allied Workers Union (RAWU), 1984 (Box 14, Folder 185)
  - Rhodes University, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 186)
  - Sarmcol Worker's Cooperative (SAWCO), undated (Box 14, Folder 187)
  - Save the Press Committee, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 188)
  - Section 29 Parent's Committee, undated (Box 14, Folder 189)
  - Society for Democratic Education, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 190)
  - Sono, Themba, undated
    See: Series III. Non-Parliamentary/Opposition/Pressure Groups, 1961-1991 Folder 213 - 215
  - South African Allied Worker's Union (SAAWU), 1981-1984 (Box 14, Folder 191)
  - South African Amateur Athletic Union, undated (Box 14, Folder 192)
  - South African Catholic Bishops Conference, 1974-1985 (Box 14, Folder 193)
  - South African Chemical Workers' Union (SACWU), 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 194)
  - South African Communist Party (SACP), 1962-1989 (Box 14, Folder 195 - 195a)
    See also: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 31-32 See also: Series IX. Posters and Printed Materials, 1968-1991 Box 33-34
  - South African Congress of Trade Unions (SACTU), 1973-1990 (Box 14, Folder 196)
  - South African Council of Churches (SACC), 1982-1989 (Box 14, Folder 197)
  - South African Council on Sport (SACOS), 1986 (Box 14, Folder 198)
  - South African Democratic Writers' Federation, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 199)
  - South African Film and Television Technicians' Association (SAFTTA), 1983-1985 (Box 14, Folder 200)
  - South African Footplate Staff Association, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 201)
  - South African History Archive, 1990-1991 (Box 15, Folder 202)
  - South African Iron and Steel Worker's, Shipbuilder's and Welder's Society, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 203)
  - South African National Student's Congress (SANSCO), undated (Box 15, Folder 204)
  - South African Railways and Harbours Workers Union (SARHWU), undated (Box 15, Folder 205)
  - South African Society of Bank Officials, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 206)
  - South African Student and Press Union, undated (Box 15, Folder 207)
  - South African Student's Organisation (SASO)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 15, Folder 208)
    - 1971 (Box 15, Folder 209)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 15, Folder 210)
  - South African Youth Congress (SAYCO), 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 211)
  - South African Youth Revolutionary Council, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 212)